[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the Financial Committees?",
    "options": ["The Public Accounts Committee is  described as a ‘continuous economy committee’.", "The Estimates Committee lacks the expert assistance of the CAG", "The Committee on Public Undertakings examine the technical matters related to  Public Undertakings with the help of technical experts", "Public Accounts Committee can not examine the accounts of autonomous and semi-autonomous bodies, even the audit of which is conducted by the CAG"],
    "answer": "The Estimates Committee lacks the expert assistance of the CAG"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "Consider the following statements with respect to Judiciary in India:1. The court of Munsiff decides both civil and criminal cases.2. The district judge possesses original and appellate jurisdiction in both civil as well as criminal matters. Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
    "answer": "(b) 2 only"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct with respect to the High Courts of Union territories?\n1. The High Court of Delhi was established by the Constitution under Article 239AA.2. Establishing a High Court for a Union Territory would require a constitutional amendment.Select the correct answer using the code given below",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
    "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Consider the following statements :1. Currently there are 25 High Courts in India. 2. President determines the strength of a high court from time to time.3. A High Court judge holds office until he  attains the age of 65 years.Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
    "answer": "(b) 1 and 2 only"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "Consider the following statements:1. The President may with the consent of the Government of a State entrust to those officers in a state, functions in relation to any matter to which the executive power of the Union extends.2. The Governor of a State, with the consent of the Government of India, can entrust the Union Government with functions in relation to matters under which the executive power of that State extends.Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
    "answer": "(b) 1 and 2 only"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "Which of the following is/are the exclusive powers of Lok Sabha?1. Vote of demand for grants2. Introduction of Constitution Amendment bill 3. Creation of All India Service  Select the correct answer using the code given below",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
    "answer": "(a) 1 only"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Consider the following statements with reference to the responsibility of ministers:\n1. When the Lok Sabha passes a no-confidence motion against the council of ministers, each minister needs to resign separately.\n2. The principle of collective responsibility means that if any minister disagrees with a cabinet decision and is not prepared to defend it, he must resign.\n3. There is no provision in the Constitution for the system of legal responsibility of a minister.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
    "options": ["(a) 3 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 2 only", "(d) 1 and 3 only"],
    "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only"
},
{
  "id": 8,
  "question": "In which among the following cases does the Prime Minister advise the President?\n1. Proroguing of the sessions of the Parliament\n2. Dissolution of the Lok Sabha\n3. Appointment of Comptroller and Auditor General of India.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
},
{
  "id": 9,
  "question": "With an aim to break down the border barriers between the states, the Constitution of India under Article 301 declares that trade, commerce and intercourse throughout the territory of India shall be free but with few exceptions.\nWith reference to the above paragraph, consider the following statements:\n1. Parliament can impose restrictions on the freedom of trade, commerce, or intercourse between the states in the public interest.\n2. Parliament may give preference to one state over another state in the case of scarcity of goods in any part of India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2"
},
{
  "id": 10,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the parliamentary privileges available to the members:\n1. They cannot be arrested during the session of Parliament for both civil and criminal offences.\n2. The presiding officer of the house has the final authority in deciding matters of breach of privileges.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
}
,{
  "id": 11,
  "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The Constitution of India empowers State Governments to borrow only from domestic sources.\n2. A state cannot raise any loan without the consent of the Centre if there is still outstanding loan made to the state by the Centre.\n3. The residuary power of taxation is vested in the Parliament.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 3 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
},{
  "id": 12,
  "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct with reference to the 69th Constitutional Amendment Act which provided special status to the Union Territory of Delhi?\n1. The Legislative Assembly can make laws on all the matters of the State List and Concurrent List except the three matters of the State List, that is, public order, police and land.\n2. Chief Minister and other Ministers are appointed by the Lieutenant Governor.\n3. In the case of difference of opinion between the Lieutenant Governor and his ministers, the opinion of the Lieutenant Governor will prevail.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1, 2 and 3", "(c) 2 only", "(d) 1 and 2 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
},{
  "id": 13,
  "question": "Which of the following committees is not chaired by the speaker of the Lok Sabha?\n(a) Business Advisory Committee\n(b) Committee on Private Members’ Bills and Resolutions\n(c) Rules Committee\n(d) General Purposes Committee",
  "options": ["(a) Business Advisory Committee", "(b) Committee on Private Members’ Bills and Resolutions", "(c) Rules Committee", "(d) General Purposes Committee"],
  "answer": "(b) Committee on Private Members’ Bills and Resolutions"
},{
  "id": 14,
  "question": "Consider the following statements with regard to the office of the Prime Minister:\n1. A person who is not a member of either House of the Parliament cannot be appointed as the Prime Minister.\n2. As long as the Prime Minister enjoys majority support in the Lok Sabha, he/she can not be dismissed by the President on any grounds.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
},{
  "id": 15,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the council of ministers:\n1. The Speaker of the Lok Sabha administers the oath of office to all the ministers.\n2. The Council of Ministers is collectively responsible to both the houses of the Parliament.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
},{
  "id": 16,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the office of the Prime Minister:\n1. A person should prove his majority in the Lok Sabha before his appointment as the Prime Minister\n2. Prime Minister holds office during the pleasure of the President\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
},{
  "id": 17,
  "question": "Consider the following statements about Indian Federalism:\n1. Indian federalism has been called asymmetric due to the uneven power share between all the states on one side and the center on the other.\n2. Federalism was held as a part of the basic structure for the first time in the S. R. Bommai Case, 1994.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
},{
  "id": 18,
  "question": "The power to make laws with reference to which of the following subjects lies only with the Parliament, and not with the State legislatures?\n1. Prescribing residence as a condition for certain employments in a State\n2. Empowering subordinate courts to issue writs for enforcement of fundamental rights.\n3. Laws on Preventive Detention\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only"
},{
  "id": 19,
  "question": "Which of the following is/are the features of an integrated judicial system in India?\n1. Decisions of the Supreme Court are binding on all courts.\n2. Separation of the judiciary from the executive\n3. Power of High court to hear appeals from lower courts.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only"
},{
  "id": 20,
  "question": "The committee/commission was formed to examine thoroughly the various issues in Center-state relations. It recommended the establishment of an Inter-State Council under Article 263 of the Constitution for the first time.\nWhich of the following committees/commission is referred to in the above paragraph?",
  "options": ["(a) Punchhi Commission", "(b) Khusro Committee", "(c) First Administrative Reforms Commission", "(d) Sarkaria Commission"],
  "answer": "(c) First Administrative Reforms Commission"
}
,{
  "id": 21,
  "question": "In which of the following parameters, Minister of State and Cabinet Ministers are equivalent in stature?\n1. Oath\n2. Removal\n3. Accountability to Lok Sabha\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1, 2 and 3", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 2 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 1, 2 and 3"
},{
  "id": 22,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the financial powers of the Governor:\n1. Money bill in the state legislature can be introduced only with his prior permission.\n2. He can make advances out of the Consolidated Fund of the State.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
},
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Which among the following Cabinet Committees is not chaired by the Prime Minister?\n(a) Political Affairs Committee\n(b) Economic Affairs Committee\n(c) Appointments Committee\n(d) Parliamentary Affairs Committee",
    "options": ["(a) Political Affairs Committee", "(b) Economic Affairs Committee", "(c) Appointments Committee", "(d) Parliamentary Affairs Committee"],
    "answer": "(d) Parliamentary Affairs Committee"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "Consider the following pairs:\nCabinet Committee | Currently Chaired by\n1. Cabinet Committee on Political Affairs : Minister of Home Affairs\n2. Cabinet Committee on Security : Minister of Defence\n3. Cabinet Committee on Accommodation : Prime Minister\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?",
    "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 2 only", "(d) None"],
    "answer": "(d) None"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological sequence of the events related to the NCT of Delhi?\n1. Creation of National Capital Territory of Delhi under 69th Constitutional Amendment Act.\n2. Delhi classified under Part C states, which were centrally administered.\n3. Creation of Union Territory of Delhi under the 7th Constitutional Amendment Act.\n4. Creation of Delhi Metropolitan Council\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
    "options": ["(a) 2-4-3-1", "(b) 3-2-1-4", "(c) 2-3-4-1", "(d) 2-3-1-4"],
    "answer": "(c) 2-3-4-1"
}
,{
  "id": 26,
  "question": "In the context of the Indian parliament, which of the following will lapse on the dissolution of Lok Sabha?\n1. A bill passed by the Lok Sabha but pending in the Rajya Sabha\n2. A bill pending in the Rajya Sabha but not passed by the Lok Sabha\n3. All pending assurances that are to be examined by the Committee on Government Assurances\nSelect the correct answer from the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 2 and 3 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
}
,



{
  "id": 27,
  "question": "Which of the following statements regarding the introduction of private member's bill in the House of Parliament:\n1. One month's notice is required for its introduction in the house.\n2. It is generally introduced and discussed on Fridays.\n3. A member cannot introduce more than four bills in the session.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
}
,


{
  "id": 28,
  "question": "The Indian Federalism can be best explained in terms of:",
  "options": ["(a) an agreement between the center and constituent units in order to set up a federation.", "(b) dependence of state government on the centre for all funds, functions and functionaries.", "(c) constitutional devolution of powers to the state governments.", "(d) extraordinary powers with center to unilaterally change the federal principles of the constitution."],
  "answer": "(c) constitutional devolution of powers to the state governments."
}
,

{
  "id": 29,
  "question": "With reference to the office of Governor, consider the following statements:\n1. In case of a bicameral legislature, Governor can issue ordinance only when both the houses are not in session.\n2. He enjoys personal immunity from legal liability for his official acts.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
}
,{
  "id": 30,
  "question": "Consider the following statements about the Rajya Sabha:\n1. Since Independence only once did a Presiding officer of Rajya Sabha cast his vote.\n2. It never adopted a motion for removal of a Judge.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
}
,

{
  "id": 31,
  "question": "Lok Adalats do not have jurisdictions in respect of which of the following cases?\n1. Land acquisition cases\n2. Matters relating to divorce\n3. Bank recovery cases\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1, 2 and 3", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1 only"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
}
,

{
  "id": 32,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court (SC):\n1. A dispute arising out of any pre-Constitutional treaty, agreement, and engagement comes under Original Jurisdiction.\n2. Cases involving interpretation of the Constitution in civil and criminal matters come under the Appellate Jurisdiction.\n3. Appeal by Special Leave is available in matters of civil and criminal cases but not in constitutional.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 1 and 3 only", "(c) 2 only", "(d) 2 and 3 only"],
  "answer": "(c) 2 only"
},
{
  "id": 33,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding parliamentary legislation in the state list when the Rajya Sabha passes the resolution to that effect:\n1. It can make law on any subject enumerated in the State list when the Rajya Sabha passes the resolution with a special majority.\n2. The law remains in force till it is repealed by an Act of the Parliament.\n3. It restricts the power of the state legislature to make laws on the same matter.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
}
,
{
  "id": 34,
  "question": "Which of the following are the conditions for the appointment as the District Judge?\n1. He should not already be in service of the Central or state government.\n2. He should have been an advocate or a pleader for seven years.\n3. He should be recommended by the high court for an appointment.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1, 2 and 3", "(b) 1 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 2 only", "(d) 2 and 3 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 1, 2 and 3"
}
,
{
  "id": 35,
  "question": "With reference to 'curative petition', consider the following statements:\n1. It is a judicial innovation and not mentioned under Indian constitution.\n2. It must only be heard by the bench of five judges including Chief Justice of India and the judges who dismissed review petition.\n3. Such a petition need to be filed within 6 months from the date of judgement or order.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 2 and 3 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
}
,
{
  "id": 36,
  "question": "Which of the following bodies are headed by the Prime Minister?\n1. National Integration Council\n2. National Water Resource Council\n3. Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)\n4. National Ganga River Basin Authority (NGRBA)\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 4 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 3 and 4 only", "(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
}
,


{
  "id": 37,
  "question": "Consider the following statements about the Central Council of Ministers:\n1. The Constitution does not classify categories of the council of Ministers.\n2. The total number of ministers, including the Prime Minister, in the Council of Ministers, shall not exceed 15% of the total strength of the Parliament.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(a) 1 only"
}
,

{
  "id": 38,
  "question": "Consider the following statements with reference to Contempt of Court:\n1. The expression 'Contempt of court’ has not been defined by the Constitution.\n2. A court subordinate to the High court has no powers to initiate proceedings against a person for contempt of court.\n3. Publication of matter that lowers the authority of a court comes under the Criminal Contempt of court.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
}
,

{
  "id": 39,
  "question": "Consider the following statements with respect to Jammu And Kashmir Reorganization Act 2019 and the related rules:\n1. The Union Territory of Jammu and Kashmir will have a Council of Ministers of not more than fifteen percent of the total number of members in the Assembly.\n2. Anyone who has resided for a period of 15 years in the UT of J&K is considered as a domicile in the UT of Jammu and Kashmir.\n3. It empowers the Union Parliament to adopt any one or more of the languages in use in the UT of J&K or Hindi as the official language for all the official purposes.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(b) 2 only"
}
,

{
  "id": 40,
  "question": "Which of the following has/have aided in promoting cooperative federalism in India?\n1. Setting up of NITI Aayog\n2. 101st Constitutional Amendment Act\n3. Supreme Court Judgement in Kharak Singh vs State of Uttar Pradesh, 1962\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 1 and 2 only", "(c) 2 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(b) 1 and 2 only"
}
,
{
  "id": 41,
  "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. ‘Extra-territorial’ legislation can only be made by the Parliament of India.\n2. The power to make laws with respect to residuary matters lies with the Parliament of India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2"
}
,

{
  "id": 42,
  "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The term of Prime Minister is five years.\n2. The constitution provides that the President has to appoint the leader of the majority party in the Lok Sabha as Prime Minister.\n3. Nominated members of the Rajya sabha cannot become the Prime Minister.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are not correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 3 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
}
,

{
  "id": 43,
  "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. According to the Constitution of India a distinguished jurist can be appointed as a judge of a High Court.\n2. The Governor of a State administers the oath of office to the judges of the High court of the concerned State.\n3. The salaries and pensions of judges of a High Court are determined by the President.\nWhich of the statements given is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 1 only", "(d) 2 and 3 only"],
  "answer": "(a) 2 only"
}
,
{
  "id": 44,
  "question": "Consider the following statements with reference to the Estimates Committee of the Parliament:\n1. It cannot suggest alternative policies in order to bring about efficiency in administration as there is no representation of ministers in the committee.\n2. It lacks the expert assistance of the CAG which is available to the Public Accounts Committee.\n3. The chairman of the committee is appointed by the Speaker from amongst its members and he is invariably from the ruling party.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 2 and 3 only", "(b) 1 only", "(c) 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(a) 2 and 3 only"
}
,
{
  "id": 45,
  "question": "With reference to the comparison between the Rajya Sabha and the State Legislative Councils, consider the following statements:\n1. The President nominates around five percent of members of the total strength of the Rajya Sabha while in the case of legislative councils, more than fifteen percent of the total members are nominated by the Governor.\n2. While Rajya Sabha is the revising body for ordinary bills of the Lok Sabha, the state legislative council is only an advisory body.\n3. The Constitution of India has fixed the maximum strength of both the Rajya Sabha as well as state legislative councils.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
}
,
{
  "id": 46,
  "question": "With reference to the provisions regarding the office of the Prime Minister given in the Constitution of India, consider the following statements:\n1. The term of office of the Prime Minister is five years.\n2. The salary and allowances of the Prime Minister are determined by the President.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
}
,


{
  "id": 47,
  "question": "Which of the following is/are the possible reasons for appointing the Governor rather than electing him?\n1. To prevent friction between Governor and Chief Minister.\n2. To reduce the election expenses involved in the election process\n3. It would discourage separatist tendencies in the States.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 2 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
},
{
  "id": 48,
  "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the division of power of taxation between the Centre and the States:\n1. The power of taxation on subjects enumerated in the concurrent list lies exclusively with the Parliament.\n2. The power to impose taxes on subjects not enumerated in any list is vested with the state legislatures.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"],
  "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
}
,{
  "id": 49,
  "question": "Which of the following statements is not correct regarding the Speaker?",
  "options": ["(a) While deciding upon anti-defection cases under the Tenth Schedule, the speaker acts as a Tribunal.", "(b) In India institutions of speaker originated under the provisions of the Indian Councils Act, 1909.", "(c) His conduct can not be discussed except on a substantive motion.", "(d) After Independence, the Speaker never used his casting vote"],
  "answer": "(b) In India institutions of speaker originated under the provisions of the Indian Councils Act, 1909."
}
,
{
  "id": 50,
  "question": "Which of the following circumstances may lead to the resignation of the Council of Ministers?",
  "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 1 and 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"],
  "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
}




]
